<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><guide><text id="13" class="indentedHeader">Why Climb in Sydney?:
Spoilt rotten bastards. Imagine that, a multicultural city of five million people, with all the lashings of the modern world, snugly wrapped around a picture-perfect crystal blue harbour, blessed with idyllic weather, with pockets of vibrant green bushland sprouting the odd sandstone escarpment for your climbing convenience. You might almost have the world's most livable city.

But with world class climbing only an hour or two away in the Blue Mountains, Nowra and Point Perpendicular, why would you hang around home and climb? Well, convenience really. Maybe you just want to go climbing for the arvo? Does riding your bike to a crag have appeal? Maybe you're just visiting the town for a few days and don't have the means to get further afield? Perhaps the weather gods are cloaking the mountains in white misty wetness, Nowra is sweating in its own humidity or you've run out of spare undies for the Point. 

Whatever your motivation, Sydney is stocked full of a variety of great climbing on small sandstone outcrops scattered throughout the city. With the rock rarely giving solid "trad" placements, the dominant climbing style is "sport". (But there are plenty of quality trad climbs around, so don't sell your rack just yet.) It was not always this way, and many crags throughout this guide were "equipped" decades ago, with technology and attitudes of a different time. In recent years there has been a concerted effort to bring Sydney climbing, lumbering and recalcitrant as it is, into the modern ethos. Hopefully this guide will help you make sense of it all. 
</text><text id="16" class="indentedHeader">What to Expect:
At the popular crags (look for yellow stars under each region's crag list), expect quality sandstone climbing in a peaceful suburban setting. Many of the crags lurk under the tree canopies, tucked behind houses or hidden away in parks and pockets of native bushland, often with river or harbour views. Walkins are generally stupidly short and cafes and icecream shops are never far away.

Refer to the individual crag notes for the style of climbing at your chosen crag. Mostly you'll need just a sport rack, but bring along a couple of cams, wires and slings for the odd mixed route. A 50m rope is plenty enough. You'll also need bolt plates for many climbs - check the Things You Need To Know chapter if you don't know what these are! For the trad climbs, a standard rack of cams, hexes and nuts will do, nothing is too long or requiring any specialised gear.

For those crags where the bolts are old and manky, these climbs are best treated as toprope problems. For toproping you may need a swag of slings or a short rope, and a couple of bolt plates. Otherwise bring a couple of bouldering mats and buckets of courage!

The rock in the 'burbs is generally OK, but its the sea cliffs that will stain your lycra brown. Take extra care on the sea cliffs and treat all protection (and holds) as suss.

Whatever you do, have fun - And don't be a d*ck and wreck it for other people. Take home all your trash, keep the noise down when close to houses, don't park in a way that blocks access for locals and their visitors, and generally keep a low profile. These simple courtesies will keep the crags open for everyone to enjoy!

</text><text id="3" class="indentedHeader">Weather:
Late autumn, winter and early spring (April to September) are definitely the best times to climb in the Sydney region. The temperature almost never drops below zero degrees Celsius in the Sydney basin, and the weather is usually pretty stable during this time. It can get pretty bitter at shady crags that catch the wind (eg. Bangor West), but generally it's always possible to climb during the cooler months. Friction on the sandstone is also at its best when it's cold.

Climbing in summer is a real battle against the grease. It tends to be unbearably hot (35+ degrees Celsius is pretty common) and wet as well, with stinking hot humid days followed by seemingly endless days of torrential downpour that are barely any cooler. The shady south and east facing crags are the pick during the hot months, with Narrabeen Slabs and the Cathedral being good options. The sea cliffs are also a good option, since they are usually in shade by mid afternoon and swimming is usually possible. The boulders on Palm Beach are probably the pick of these areas.

Another disincentive for climbing during summer is the sea slime, which coats most of the sea cliffs and crags near the ocean. This can also happen at other times of the year, particularly if the prevailing weather is easterly.

When choosing your crag, I should point out what is obvious to locals but not necessarily to northern hemisphere visitors. The sun rises in the east, sets in the west, and the north faces catch the sun all day long. So in winter seek a north facing cliff and in summer a south facing one.

Good sun protection (sunscreen, hats etc.) is an absolute must during summer. Foreign visitors should be particularly careful not to underestimate the power of the sun.

The sandstone found in Sydney is quite porous, meaning that many of the crags seep during and particularly after rain. The rock also has a tendency to soften somewhat when wet, so take care if you're cranking on small holds after rain.

The Australian Bureau of Meteorology website is an excellent source of detailed information on Sydney's climate. Amongst other things they provide an up to date Sydney weather forecast and an almost-realtime Sydney Rain Radar.</text><text id="4">The following two graphs give a bit of an idea of Sydney's climate throughout the year (courtesy also of the Bureau).</text><image id="5" src="temperature_small.gif" /><image id="6" src="rainfall_small.gif" /><text id="11" class="indentedHeader">Getting Around:

A car helps, but driving in Sydney can be a pain (and rather tense, especially for visitors!).

If you don't have a car, some crags can be accessed by public transport.
The best resource for planning a trip is http://www.131500.com

Riding a bike is also an option. Some crags are near bike paths and you could combine riding with public transport. Check out the RTA cycleway maps online.

</text><text id="18" class="indentedHeader">The Best Areas:

If you are just visiting and want to sample the best climbing around Sydney, check out the following areas:
- Barrenjoey (right by the beach, noice)
- Berowra (something for everyone, good for winter)
- Bangor (good for easy grades)
- Bonnet Bay (fab sport climbing right in the burbs)
- The Cathedral </text><text id="17" class="indentedHeader">Grading:
&lt;Insert Grade Comparison Chart&gt;</text><text id="7" class="indentedHeader">Sport Climbing &amp; Fixed Protection:
Yes some of the climbs in this guide are sport climbs. These climbs are marked with the Þ symbol. This generally implies the route is adequately protected using in-situ bolt protection and has a lower off. However one person's opinion of what constitutes "adequate protection" may not be yours. Also, some people consider any climb with fixed protection a sport climb, even if there is no lower off, or you may need to place the odd piece of protection. Most importantly, there are many, many BAD bolts out there, particularly if the climb was bolted a few years ago.

Do not assume any climb marked with the Þ symbol is safe to climb or is completely equipped. You must assess the climb and its fixed protection before climbing the route. If in doubt, top rope it or do something else.
Many climbs that are not marked as a sport climb do have fixed protection. The local ethic for many years has been to place fixed protection where no natural protection exists, but leave otherwise naturally protected climbing to be protected using nuts, cams, etc. The variable and unreliable nature of the rock in Sydney has led to enthusiasm for fixed protection that would be scandalous in other parts of Australia.

Where there is no lower off, you should top out, create a three point equalised belay off whatever is available, and bring your buddy up, then refer to the guidebook for the best descent option.

Some climbs are marked with the "X", to indicate known safety issues. Either the bolts are known to be bad, the rock is friable, or something else is just plain bad.
Please let us know if you are aware of rebolting that is not indicated in this guide, or climbs with bad bolts which are not marked as such!</text><text id="8">Here are some of the bolts you may encounter (TODO add pics &amp; desc)</text><text id="10" class="indentedHeader">Access Issues:
There are a number of land managers who oversee the climbing areas in this guide. One of the incentives for publishing a complete up-to-date guide is to inform everybody of the current state of play, and to encourage climbers to behave in ways that will increase our chances of keeping access open.

The land managers are private land owners, city councils and the NSW National Parks and Wildlife Service.

Land managers are concerned about liability and environmental impacts (including tracks, erosion, fixed protection and vegetation clearing). Bureaucrats feel obliged to control or prohibit activities for various reasons, such as minimizing their workload, reducing risk, bowing to special interest groups, or simply because an activity falls outside their narrow view of acceptable recreation. Regardless of your own opinions, the reality is that land managers can act to prohibit climbing and so we need to deal with it.

Climbing in Sydney Harbour National Park is currently (January 2011) banned. Elsewhere climbing is discouraged by NPWS in Royal National Park and most parts of Ku-ring-gai Chase National Park. The one exception in this latter park is Barrenjoey Headland where climbing is permitted under the existing Plan of Management.

The Royal and Ku-ring-gai Plans of Management state that unless specifically approved in the Plan then climbing is only permitted with written consent from the Director General and is subject to payment of fees and any conditions considered necessary. However experience to date is that such permission is generally not forthcoming. Refer to the access notes for crags affected by this for more information.

Many of the crags in this guide are close to peoples homes. When parking, do not block driveways or park in such a way as to fill up a street and force locals to park further away. Keep noise to a minimum and keep a low profile. Basically don't give a local a reason to want climbing to be banned in their area.

If developing a new crag, be mindful that a row of shiny rings and chalk up a rock face might in your eyes be a beautiful thing, but for the average ground-based punter its an eyesore and an environmental impact. Forget the argument that roads, walking tracks, hand rails, power lines and suburbia are all impacts on the environment too, its an amusing argument with plenty of truth but sadly it does not hold weight in public debates involving non-climbers. So minimize your impact by not developing cliffs right next to popular walking tracks or in plain view of the general public.</text><text id="9" class="indentedHeader">Symbols and Abbreviations:
Þ - Sport climb
X - Danger! Danger! Crap old bolts, crap rock, loose blocks, snakes, bullants, dragons!
Ψ - Route name made up, no FA details submitted.
L - left
R - right
BR - bolt runner (might need a hanger)
FH - fixed hanger
RB - ring bolt
BB - bolt belay
DBB - double bolt belay</text><text id="15" class="indentedHeader">Acknowledgements:
This guide is, at least initially, a reincarnation of the "Sun, Surf and Sandstone" website put together by Peter Monks, who over the years gathered and organised information provided by the hundreds of climbers around Sydney. A big thankyou to Peter who provided the raw data from which gave us a starting point. Various people have been putting recent updates into the ACA database and those updates are now here too. In addition, I've sourced other info from the SRC website and various printed guides floating around. Where possible I have acknowledged the key contributors under each section. Mike Law, Neil Montieth, Dave Noble and Niall Doherty have helped with some initial updates, and Kevin Westren has been working through the crag access issues. But essentially the whole work is the product of the Sydney climbing community working together. Special thanks though to Jon Nermut who pioneered the software and has helped us get it up and running. Andrew Clarke has also helped with systems administration.</text></guide>