<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><guide guidestars="***"><header intro="The Cathedral is proabaly the best urban crag near Sydney, in a beautiful setting on the banks of the Woronora River right in the heart of the Shire. It's is possibly the highest crag in Sydney town with a height of twenty-odd meters in some sections, with unusual (solid and very frictional) rock. There is almost something for everyone, from grade 27 cracks, great sporty little 16s, and heap of low 20 walls. Trad climbers and sport climbers will both enjoy the place. The area is very shady, not only from facing south but also from thick vine covered jungle. Bring mozzie repellent in summer and probably avoid altogether during a wet winter. One person has had ticks here." name="The Cathedral" rock="Sandstone Climbing" sun="" id="1" access="Park at the end of Shackel Rd, Bangor. Please don't fill up the street, leave plenty of room for locals to park (if it's packed, park 50m further up the hill). Follow the track down 6m then left (East) 10m, diag right for a bit and across to the other side of the gully (about 50m all up). Walk down another 40m till you pass a small line of rocks on the left, at this point go diagionally left for 30m (across log and left) then pretty much straight down the hill to top of cliff. About 5 minutes. Either rap in or go right and down gully       &#xA;&#xA;The alternative (original) way involves walking along the river and is a bit scrubby and eroded, but pretty. Park in Prince Edward Park in Woronora (or walk down the hill from Sutherland railway station). Cross the footbridge, turn left and follow the track along the river for about 1km. Although you walk past the right hand slabs first, they aren't as obvious as the main wall, which looms above the track about 20m to the right. Bash up through the jungle to the base of the crag. Maybe 20 minutes walking.  If you've got a boat or kayak, paddle in!" acknowledgement="Bundy, Mikl's guide and Sun Surf Sandstone" walk="Steep 5 mins or scrubby flat 20 mins" camping="" /><image id="62" src="cataxx.jpg" width="400" /><text class="heading3" id="17">
Main Wall
</text><text id="18">
Climbs described left to right after you come down the descent gully.There is an evil descent chimney at the right end of the main cliff (maybe garde 10), but it's desperate and it's only 3 minutes to walk off down the gully on the far left. Besides, most of the climbs have lower-offs here.
</text><text id="82">Left end of main wall</text><image id="86" src="cathleftend.jpg" width="700" /><climb extra="Þ" grade="19" id="52" length="10m" name="C Slab" fa="?" stars="*">Start below the boulder. Up the slab  past Ubolts to lower off. Thin at top
</climb><climb id="79" name="mikl's arete project">Pointy arete 6m R of CS</climb><climb grade="18" id="50" length="12m" name="Layback Crack" stars="*" fa="?">
Start: 10m right of CS, in a right facing layback corner that stops at 8m.  Head up the corner  to BR at top, then traverse right and up (BR) the arete to a lower off. Needs a bit of traffic, bring thin to hand sized cams
</climb><climb id="83" stars="*" name="Head Injuries" length="8m" grade="13" extra="Þ	" fa="Graham Fairbairn 1989">Walk down and right 20m and up to right facing corner crack</climb><climb extra="Þ" fa="Graham Fairbairn 1989" grade="21" id="49" length="10m" name="Young Bumblies" stars="***">Slabby classic. Climb H.I. and head left and belay on Ubolt. Up flake and steep wall (4 Ubolts). Lower off all the way to the deck</climb><image id="87" src="cathedraltopo.jpg" width="700" /><climb id="74" stars="**" name="Surface Paradise" length="20m" grade="22" extra="Þ   " fa="Mikl 2011">Start up Head Injuries and up wall above, powerful then delicate</climb><climb id="75" name="Surface Paradise DS" grade="23" fa="mikl 2011" stars="*" extra="3Þ      " length="10m">Up seam right of Head Injuries and up arete to join Surface Paradise. A few weird moves to a sloping ledge above the 3rd Ubolt. The fin on the left side of the ledge is on. Stay on the right side of the arete above to join SP at the break..</climb><climb extra="Þ" fa="Kent Heffernan 1989" grade="21" id="47" length="18m" name="The Dynamic Duo" stars="**">Start 2m R of HI, just left of a wide crack. Head left up the flake and onto the steep wall. There 'may' be some bridging inot the corner but can be done without at 23.  </climb><climb extra="Þ" fa="David Barnes 1990" grade="23" id="46" length="16m" name="Jaded Cravings" stars="*">Start 3m R of HI, in wide crack. Up the EZ arete. Gather your thoughts in a small cave, then bounce on to the wall and up </climb><image id="84" src="Cathedral_Hercules.jpg" /><climb fa="Graham Fairbairn 1989 to bulge (which is probabaly the crux), Extension to top by mikl 1990" grade="23" id="43" length="15m" name="Anticoagulant" stars="***" extra="Þ">Up corner 15m R of HI (confusingly marked SSS) to cave then left and continue up leaning crack bulge and on to top. Weird, funky fun. </climb><climb extra="Þ" fa="Mike Law 1991" grade="27" id="44" length="8m" name="Bordella de Merde" stars="**">The 3 RB's to double RB lower off above Anticoagulant, a great line, the pinch out right is on (rebolted 2008)</climb><climb id="64" name="Project mikl poxy Left Varient" stars="*" length="15m" grade="" extra="4Þ">Start up corner as for Anticoagulant and Hercules then up through caves to tenuous finish on line of bolts a meter left of Hercules. </climb><climb extra="5Þ" fa="Kent Heffernan 1989" grade="22" id="41" length="15m" name="Hercules" stars="**">Originally started as for Imogen, but extra bolts in that means most people missed the crux by bridging up groove and stepping left. Easier to start as for Anticoagulant in easy corner (with initials SSS for some reason!). Up, then step right and up line of bolts.</climb><climb extra="Þ" fa="Mike Law 1990" grade="23" id="42" length="25m" name="Hercules Direct Finish" stars="***">From the top of Hercules, blast up the arete past hard move to slabby finish to lower off (rebolted 2008)</climb><image id="58" src="1716.jpg" width="600" /><text id="59">Fat Bear on the FA of the classic Imogen. Pic by Doddy.</text><climb id="57" name="Imogen" stars="**" length="15m" grade="22" extra="Þ" fa="Jason Lammers 5-11-2008">Start just left of Cathedral Cave. Straight up blunt arete. Way cool rock climbing.</climb><climb id="71" name="Fat Crack" length="30" grade="?">Wide squeeze chimney corner crack which may or may not have been climbed. Thrutchy!</climb><climb extra="Þ" fa="David Barnes 1989-09" grade="15" id="39" length="8m" name="Axe Grinder">Probally a bit of a pain to get to. Rap in from trees on top of cliff to hanging belay off rings and old carrots. 3 RB to Double RB lower off. Nice and airy up there. </climb><climb id="55" name="Bundy's Been Boltin'" stars="*" length="15m" grade="20" extra="Þ  " fa="Jason Lammers 2007">Start just left of the Cathedral cave. Only 20 to the first lower off. The one move extension to the second lower-offs is 22. From here you can get into the wide crack and thrutch up then go right to join Axe Grinder at 23 (Cameron Taylor, The Shute).</climb><text id="38">
The large chossy cave located just here is called The Cathedral, and gives the crag its name.
</text><climb fa="Graham Fairbairn 1989" grade="19" id="37" length="25m" name="Wacky Tabacci" stars="***" extra="Þ  ">
If you like this sort of thing, this is the sort of thing you'll like. A classic with exposed climbing on good holds with 'sporting' pro, but there are a few chimney moves so long pants recommended. The obvious chimney to the right of The Cathedral cave. Hardest getting to and past the 2nd Ubolt (you can use a medium cam for courage, but remember that you can't fall out of these things). Easiest to face right and use the good holds on the right arete. After the roof step out onto the left arete past a slightly hidden Ubolt to lower off.
</climb><image id="88" src="cathedral 039.jpg" width="700" /><text id="89">Nathan on Wacki tabacci, one of the old bolts is seen between his hands.</text><climb id="63" name="Retro Crack" length="25m" grade="20" fa="FRA Mikl 2011, but may have been done before on trad." stars="**" extra="Þ     ">The bolted crack line 1.5m left of Get Out of Town. Mostly laybacking and climbing the left arete, but a jamb or two may be needed. Could easily be lead on large natural gear if you don't like Ubolts. The top half had previously been bolted (and probably traversed in from one the cracks on the right)</climb><image id="90" src="cathedral 102.jpg" width="700" /><text id="91">Rob Hodyl demonstrating how to climb wide cracks in the rain on Retro Crack</text><text id="34">
The following two climbs cross each other at the pea pod at half height.  A good variant is to start up V, step left to GOoT at about 5m and then follow it to the top.
</text><climb fa="Kent Heffernan 1989" grade="20" id="36" length="25m" name="Get Out of Town" stars="**">Start on face 1m left of V. Hard off the ground to RB, and trad up to pea pod. Move right and clip Ubolt and chain on IG then right again to join line of RBs (about 2m R of crack) to lower off. 
</climb><climb fa="P. Farkas 1989" grade="18" id="35" length="25m" name="Vitez" stars="**">Start: Below the obvious recessed corner crack.
Follow crack up and over a bulge to the pea pod. Up this and follow the crack to the top past some carrots. </climb><climb id="73" name="Vitez LH finish" length="25m" grade="17" fa="unknown" stars="*">Step left onto flake above peapod and past 2 ring bolts to top</climb><image id="53" src="793.jpg" /><text id="54">Mike Law on Inchworm Groove. </text><climb fa="Mike Law 1990" grade="27" id="33" length="10m" name="Inchworm Groove" stars="*">The hardest trad line in The Shire/Sydney/NSW maybe. Start below the thin seam, tenuous come desperate moves up the groove to lower off chain at half height or on to top. .
</climb><image id="85" src="cathslabtopo.jpg" /><climb fa="Graham Fairbairn 1989" grade="18" id="31" length="20m" name="Ozone Action" stars="***">Sydney Classic trad route at the grade! Hard weird start. Take a few cams and slings Start: Below the obvious water groove / flake feature. Follow the flake line / water groove past a two RBs, sling the spike (mayybe hang some gear off it to keep it on) and throw in a cam, then either right up jugs for a few moves then back left, or straight up the flake. Cams then up flake and top wall (BR) to lower-offs or top out 
. </climb><climb fa="Graham Fairbairn 1989" grade="23" id="32" length="22m" name="Creature Feature" stars="***">Great moves on the top wll. Almost a sport climb if you sling the big jug above the second bolt on OA. As for OA for 10m (past 2 RBs and a sling runner). Then move left past hidden RB and up the thin slab past lefthand line of bolts to lower off. Don't stray into project on right. </climb><climb id="81" name="Project">Between the upper section of OA and CF</climb><climb fa="Christina Fairbairn 1989" grade="14" id="30" length="8m" name="Jack and the Beanstalk" stars="**">
Start: Left of GW at tree.
Up, using the suffering tree to start.  2 Ubolts and cam. Finish up one of the upper routes
</climb><text id="69">The next climb used to finish at the Tarmac Traverse. The tree that used to be climbed to gain the rock has now gone. </text><climb fa="Kent Heffernan 1989" grade="14?" id="29" length="8m" name="Guerrilla Warfare" extra="2Þ">
Start:  Directly below CQ.
Start used to involve the tree, but it's been massacred, so the grade is probably much higher now.  2 BRs.
</climb><climb id="68" name="Ghostrider" length="8" grade="23" fa="Jason Lammers 2006">The short hard little problem under NN.  Hard start to pocket then crimp your way to the chain under NN.  Probably easier if your tall.</climb><text id="22">
The following 5 routes all start from the Tarmac Traverse - the obvious low angle slab leading left across the middle of the wall to a belay / rap chain (clip the first bolt on CC as a runner). If it is crowded you could also belay from the ground below the intended route. The following four routes have new lower-offs, please use your own carabiners if top-roping to save wear and tear on the bolts.
</text><climb fa="Steve Turcsanyi 1989" grade="13" id="27" length="8m" name="Aero Arete">
Just right of arete. Up, using pro to the left (as for the top of OA) or clip the bolts on ST.
</climb><climb extra="3Þ" fa="Graham Fairbairn 1989" grade="16" id="26" length="8m" name="Suicidal Tendencies" stars="*">
Next route left. 3 Ubolts to lower off.</climb><climb extra="3Þ" fa="Kent Heffernan 1989" grade="16" id="25" length="8m" name="Cathedral Quack" stars="*">
Next line to the left. Up (3 Ubolts) to lower off shared with ST.  Named for a group of ducks that used to frequent the crag.
</climb><climb extra="3Þ" fa="Graham Fairbairn 1989" grade="16" id="24" length="8m" name="Neuron Nerd" stars="*">
Step right from the chains and up.
</climb><climb extra="4Þ" fa="Kent Heffernan 1989" grade="16" id="23" length="8m" name="Cosmic Cruncher" stars="*">
The right most line. Ubolts to lower off (shared with NN).
</climb><climb fa="Kent Heffernan 1989" grade="14" id="21" length="10m" name="Shoot That Dog">The chimney.Looks hard
</climb><climb extra="3Þ" fa="Graham Fairbairn 1989" grade="20" id="20" length="12m" name="Mushroom Mantle" stars="**">
Start below flake. Up the flake with a bizarre mantle near the top.  4 Ubolts and lower-off.
</climb><climb extra="3Þ" fa="Mike Law 1990" grade="24" id="19" length="12m" name="Cranking Like a Demon" stars="*">
Start left of descent chimney. Up slab and bulge (4 Ubolts) to lower off.
</climb><text class="heading3" id="1">
Right Hand Slabs
</text><text id="2">
Extending away to the right of the main wall are a series of smooth slabs.  You can walk across from the main wall, or veer off right from the open grassy area further down the hill.

Climbs described left to right, facing the cliff.
</text><climb extra="Þ" fa="Mike Law 1990" grade="23" id="3" length="12m" name="Isis" stars="**">
Start: 25m right of the main wall, Up seam to lower off. Powerful moves
</climb><climb fa="Mike Law 1990" grade="28" id="4" length="18m" name="Glacis" stars="***">
Start: 3m right of Isis.
Sustained and desparate climbing up the twin cracks.  5 BRs.
</climb><climb fa="Mike Law 1990" grade="24" id="5" length="10m" name="Moss Ghyll Grooves">
Start: Below cracks at left edge of steep wall, 20m right of G.
Up the cracks (BR).  Looks easy, but looks can be deceiving...
</climb><climb id="61" name="Take me to the Tropics" length="11m" grade="25" fa="Cam Taylor 2008">A bit contrived, up MGG then move right to double RBs</climb><climb extra="Þ" fa="Mike Law 1990" grade="25" id="6" length="15m" name="In the Groove" stars="**">
Start: Right of MGG.
Up the slab (5 BRs).
</climb><climb fa="Mike Law 1991-12" grade="23" id="7" length="20m" name="Legless">
Start: 10m right of ITG.
Hard start, traverse right to corner then straight up seam.  3 BRs and natural protection.
</climb><text id="8">
The following two unrecorded routes look hard.
</text><climb grade="??" id="9" length="20m" name="A">
The left hand route.
</climb><climb grade="23?" id="10" length="20m" name="B">
Right of A.
Up (FH and 5 BRs).
</climb><text id="11">
A creek tumbles down the hill just here.
</text><climb fa="Mike Law 1990" grade="25" id="12" length="15m" name="Spite" stars="**">
Start: Just right of the creek.
A desperate slab test piece.  3 BRs.
</climb><climb fa="Mike Law 1990" grade="20" id="13" length="10m" name="Mr Squiggle">
Start: 8m right of the creek.
Up the delicate groove, passing 2 BRs.
</climb><climb extra="Þ" fa="Mike Law 1990" grade="18" id="14" length="10m" name="Ms Pat" stars="**">
Start: 4m right of MS.
Up the delicate slab, passing 3 BRs.
</climb><climb grade="18" id="15" length="18m" name="Wire Brush and Dettol">
Start: At obvious block about 40m right of MP
Layback up block then up the left side of the arete above.
</climb><climb grade="16" id="16" length="16m" name="Tourniquet">
Start: 4m right of WBaD.
Offwidth with BR down low.
</climb></guide>